Hello everybody! This is Madhavi from Dhavi Creations!
Many have been asking me to take Fabric Painting classes, workshops and online classes
That's why I decided to make videos with complete details about Fabric Painting.
To everyone who has been waiting for my videos and to those who have been following
my videos and supporting me, I thank you very much! ðŸ™
Let's have a look at all the material you will need to start your fabric painting journey.
This is our Fabric Painting Kit.
We built this kit by collecting all of the items you will need as a one-stop shop -
so that you can easily and quickly begin practicing your art.
So today, we will learn about all of these items in detail and -
we will then see a demo on how to use them to make our paintings
This is a list of all the items you will find in the fabric painting kit.
These are instructions to transfer designs onto your cloth
These are white and yellow carbon papers
This, is a large tracing paper sheet
And, printed designs.
These include simple to detailed designs.
We will see the process of transferring these designs later in the demo
This is a 6 inch embroidery ring. This is sufficient for practice.
This is paper tape. We will need it when transferring the design.
We will see how to, in the demo.
Here are three commonly used paint brushes.
and a ball point pen and a sketch pen we will need for design tracing and transferring.
These are a few stones for practice, used in tanjore style painting
This is a small painting palette, used for colour mixing
This is a half meter semi-raw silk cloth so that you can practice immediately.
We will learn about cloth choices for our fabric painting projects in the next video.
These are 9 commonly used acrylic paints.
We included Flesh Tint / skin colour, which is used for faces and figurative paintings
And Pearl Metallic Gold colour used for Tanjore Style Fabric Painting
This is Pearl Metallic Gold 3D outliner.
We will use this to enhance our designs and for Tanjore Style paintings.
And we also provide a Fabric Medium 1
This is usually used for thinning the paint when it gets dry or thick
I have to tell you a little detail now.
In the market we find two types of paint - Acrylic colours and Fabric colours
Many are commonly confused on what paint they should choose
These paints with the blue cap are softer and are made specifically for fabric painting,
But with only a little difference, both paints work the same way.
I have been using Acrylic colours for many years now and I have faced no problems
Even if there is an issue, it must be because of the cloth and not the paint.
So you can freely use whatever paint is available to you without any doubt.
First step, we should transfer the design on to the cloth.
These are yellow and white carbon papers.
You should only use these two types of carbon papers
Never use blue or black carbon papers
Because their colour can spread and cloth, painting both can get spoiled
For our white colour cloth, we will use yellow carbon paper
For dark colour cloth, you can use white carbon paper.
Now we will transfer this lotus design on to our cloth
Because the design is already on a white paper,
we can directly transfer the design directly by using the carbon paper under it.
To prevent the design from moving,
we will use paper tape to secure the design to the cloth
If the design paper moves, you may draw double lines
which can confuse you later, while you're painting
After you secure the design to the cloth and set the carbon paper,
draw the design with a ball-point pen
Make sure you draw the complete design without drawing double lines
Before removing the paper tape,
You must confirm that the complete design is transferred
Draw any missing lines and only then you should remove the paper tape
Now we will see how to transfer a design using a tracing paper
You should first cut the tracing paper to the size of the design
Then stick it to the design paper with paper tape to prevent it from moving
Now carefully trace the design on the tracing paper with a sketch pen
After tracing the design, remove the tracing paper along with the tape
Now stick this on our cloth where we want to transfer the design
and set our carbon paper between them like this.
To be able to see the design clearly, and to prevent the tracing paper and
carbon paper from tearing, I am placing a white paper between them.
This is optional. You can transfer the design even without the white paper.
Now we will see how to setup this embroidery ring
First set the inner ring behind the cloth with our transferred design
Then, loosen the screw of the outer ring and fix it over the inner ring.
Do not tighten the screw fully yet. Tighten it slowly,
as you gently pull the cloth from the edges until all wrinkles are gone.
As you pull the cloth, make sure the thread lines are straight
If you pull the cloth too much, or if the thread lines are not straight,
there’s a chance the painting turns out crooked after you remove the ring.
You should only tighten the screw fully after you neatly set the cloth.
These are the three brushes provided in the kit.
This is a No. 1 round brush. It can be used for filling and even outlines.
This is a No. 00 round brush. This is used for outlines and small details.
This is a No. 1 flat brush. This is used for colour filling and blending.
To clean the brushes as we paint,
we should have a container of water and a cotton cloth ready.
Let's start painting now.
To first put a base coat, I'm using white colour
and filling this lotus petal with a No. 1 flat brush.